{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This President averted a strike by signing the Adamson Act to grant an eight-hour workday to railroad workers. This man oversaw the deportation of over 200 anarchists on the “Soviet Ark,” many of whom were arrested in a series of raids ordered by his attorney general, Mitchell Palmer; this President’s Espionage Act, which justified those arrests, was upheld by the Supreme Court due to wartime conditions. For ten points, name this president who led the United States through World War I.",
      "answer": "Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
    },
    {
      "question": "One side in this battle benefited from the Dowding System, which used data from Chain Home stations to produce maps. Directive No. 17 ordered one side in this battle to begin with an assault on Adlertag, or Eagle Day. Failure in this battle led to the cancellation of Operation Sealion, prompting the statement of gratitude “never [...] was so much owed by so many to so few” from Winston Churchill. For ten points, name this air battle of 1940 in which the RAF defended their home from Nazi invasion.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Britain",
        "descriptions of Nazi Germany bombing any part of the United Kingdom, including England, London, etc.",
        "the Blitz"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In response to this event, the President noted “we’ve grown used to wonders in this century,” in a speech written by Peggy Noonan; that speech became known as the “face of God” speech. This event was investigated by the Rogers Commission, which included Richard Feynman [fine-man]. Schoolteacher Christa McAuliffe was killed in this event, which was caused by O-rings that failed in low temperatures. For ten points, name this 1986 tragedy in which a space shuttle exploded.",
      "answer": [
        "Space Shuttle Challenger disaster",
        "equivalents, like explosion, crash, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In some accounts, this man gathers his army to battle the emperor Lucius after angrily refusing a Roman tribute demand. At Tintagel, this man’s father disguises himself as Gorlois to sleep with this man’s mother, Igraine. This son of Uther Pendragon is the subject of a medieval romance by Thomas Malory, in which he becomes a leader after pulling a sword from a stone. For ten points, name this owner of Excalibur, a legendary medieval king of England.",
      "answer": "King Arthur"
    },
    {
      "question": "A plaza in this city includes Cellini’s sculpture of Perseus and a copy of a statue now held in this city’s Academy of Fine Arts. Another museum in this city holds La Primavera and The Birth of Venus by Sandro Botticelli, who primarily worked in this city. A family of art patrons in this city included Lorenzo the Magnificent and Cosimo I, who commissioned this city’s Uffizi Gallery. For ten points, name this Italian city once controlled by the Medici family.",
      "answer": "Florence or Firenze"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man beat Congressman William Stanbery with a hickory cane on Pennsylvania Avenue after Stanbery suggested that this man had defrauded Native Americans. To avoid paying fees from the resulting trial, this politician fled to Mexico, where he later led the Texan Army at the Battle of San Jacinto and captured Santa Anna. For ten points, name this Texas politician, the namesake of the most populous city in Texas.",
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2003 court case ruled that Job Charnock was not the founder of this city. Lord Curzon created a monument in this city’s Dalhousie Square to commemorate an incident, of which John Zephaniah Howell wrote an account of brutalities committed in Fort William by the Nawab of Bengal. 146 prisoners were locked in a cell in this city, in which only 23 survived the conditions. British prisoners were kept in the “Black Hole” of, for ten points, what capital of West Bengal in eastern India?",
      "answer": [
        "Kolkata",
        "Calcutta",
        "additional information relating to the Black Hole of Calcutta",
        "Kolkata after “Curzon” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A building designed by this man, Wardenclyffe, was the focus of a 2012 preservation effort led by the webcomic The Oatmeal. David Bowie portrayed this real-life person in the 2006 film The Prestige. This man’s development of a system licensed by George Westinghouse led to a vicious conflict with Thomas Edison, who championed a competing system involving direct current. For ten points, name this Serbian-American scientist and inventor who names a coil that produces AC electricity.",
      "answer": "Nikola Tesla"
    },
    {
      "question": "E´douard Drumont condemned the victim of this event in his newspaper La Libre Parole. This event concerned a document called the Bordereau, which had been forged by Major Henry. Ferdinand Ester´azy’s role in this event was discovered by Georges Picquart a year after its initial suspect was imprisoned on Devil’s Island. E´mile Zola wrote the letter J’accuse as a response to, for ten points, what 1890s affair in which a Jewish French army officer was falsely imprisoned for treason?",
      "answer": "Dreyfus Affair"
    },
    {
      "question": "The unveiling of this structure’s design led James Webb and Ross Perot to withdraw support, with Perot controversially insulting its architect as an “eggroll.” An opponent of this structure called it a “gash of shame,” as its design emulates the shape of a closed wound. Frederick Hart’s Three Soldiers overlooks this memorial, of which visitors often create crayon rubbings. Maya Lin designed, for ten points, what memorial that lists the name of servicemen who died in a Southeast Asian War?",
      "answer": [
        "Vietnam Veterans Memorial",
        "descriptions of the Vietnam War memorial",
        "descriptions of the Vietnam Wall"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. A speech about Verres claims that people with this status could not be harmed if they proclaimed this status. Before being placed on trial, the Apostle Paul claimed this status to a centurion. John F. Kennedy noted that “two thousand years ago,” this status was “the proudest boast” before comparing it to being “ein Berliner.” Slaves could not hold this status unless freed. Women held only a minimal form of, for ten points, what legal status in an ancient Italian empire?",
        "answer": [
          "Roman citizenship",
          "descriptions of being a citizen of Rome"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Roman politician proclaimed the security of the statement “civis romanus sum,” or “I am a Roman citizen,” in his second pleading against Gaius Verres in 70 BC. After the death of Julius Caesar, this orator attacked Mark Antony in the Philippics.",
        "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A county in this colony was sued by James Maury in the Parson’s Cause, which involved a dispute between this state’s established Anglican clergy and its government. The defense in that case was led by a member of this colony’s legislature, the House of Burgesses, who proclaimed “Give me liberty or give me death” in 1775. Patrick Henry was a politician from, for ten points, what American colony, the most populous before the Revolution, where the House of Burgesses met in Jamestown and Williamsburg?",
        "answer": "Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A decade before declaring “Give me liberty or give me death!”, Patrick Henry gave an impassioned speech in the House of Burgesses in favor of the Virginia Resolves, a response to this 1765 act of Parliament.",
        "answer": "Stamp Act"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This site includes the Torreon tower, which was once used as an observatory, and a Popular District where commoners lived. The Huatana stone and the Room of the Three Windows at this site were dedicated to a sun god, Inti. This site is situated above the Urubamba River and was constructed as an estate for Pachacuti. Hiram Bingham studied, for ten points, what “lost city of the Incas?”",
        "answer": "Machu Picchu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hiram Bingham’s excavation of Machu Picchu was supported by this Ivy League university, where Bingham lectured.",
        "answer": "Yale University"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this empire’s colonial holdings was a company co-founded by Carl Peters and opposed by the failed Abushiri Revolt. This empire, which seized a naval base at Tsingtao from the Chinese in 1898, sent the Panther gunboat to Morocco in a failed attempt to break the Entente Cordiale alliance of two of its rivals. For ten points, name this country that engaged in a naval arms race with Great Britain and signed the 1879 Dual Alliance with Austria-Hungary, an alliance that lasted until they lost World War I.",
        "answer": "Germany or the German Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Germany’s African colonial history includes its genocide of the Herero people in this modern-day country in southwest Africa.",
        "answer": "Namibia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Tyson Yerkes thwarted this man’s efforts to build part of the London Underground through London United Tramways. This man founded New York’s Metropolitan Club and orchestrated a business deal with Elbert Gary and William Henry Moore in 1901. This man created a coalition of bankers to mitigate the Panic of 1907; earlier, he allied with the Rothschilds to sell gold to replenish the US Treasury during the Panic of 1893. For ten points, name this American financier, the namesake of a bank that merged with Chase in 2000.",
        "answer": "John Pierpont “J.P.” Morgan, Sr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "J.P. Morgan transformed this industry with the aforementioned merger of Judge Moore’s company with one owned by Andrew Carnegie, creating the world’s first billion-dollar business.",
        "answer": [
          "steel",
          "any additional information, including US Steel"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1962’s Robinson v. California, the Supreme Court used this amendment to strike down a California law criminalizing narcotic addiction. Modern applications of this amendment often rely on the idea of “evolving standards of decency.” Excessive bail is included in this amendment as an example of a prohibition found to violate “human dignity.” 1972’s Furman v. Georgia temporarily outlawed the death penalty by applying, for ten points, what Constitutional amendment that prohibits cruel and unusual punishment?",
        "answer": "8th Amendment to the US Constitution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roper v. Simmons cited the 8th Amendment while restricting the use of the death penalty for people with this characteristic. While the 26th Amendment expanded a certain right to more Americans, it did not expand that right to people with this characteristic. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": [
          "being younger than 18 years old",
          "any description of being young, a minor, a juvenile, a child, etc.",
          "being a teenager, despite the possible ambiguity that 19 presents"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location, which is called the “Six Grandfathers” by the Lakota, was seized in violation of the Treaty of Fort Laramie. The “fifth icon” of this location, Benjamin Elk, posed for photographs with thousands of tourists. Historian Doane Robinson suggested the granite pillars at the Needles for this project, but was convinced by Gutzon Borglum to use another site in the Black Hills. For ten points, name this South Dakota monument featuring the faces of four US presidents.",
        "answer": "Mount Rushmore National Monument"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earlier in his career, Gutzon Borglum worked on a monument at what Georgia site that honors Confederate leaders and hosted a KKK revival?",
        "answer": "Stone Mountain Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was disguised as a drunk flight attendant to avoid suspicion on a Bristol Britannia plane. A month earlier, as this man was getting off a bus in Buenos Aires, Peter Malkin and two other agents of Mossad tackled and abducted this man. Hannah Arendt wrote about the “banality of evil” as displayed by this man at his 1961 trial for war crimes in Jerusalem. For ten points, name this man who hid in Argentina for a decade before being executed for his role in orchestrating the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Otto Adolf Eichmann"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eichmann’s role in the Holocaust included devising a plan to deport Jews to this island in the Southern Hemisphere.",
        "answer": "Madagascar Plan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Wild West",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Female sharpshooter and partner of Frank Butler, known as “Little Sure Shot.”",
          "answer": "Annie Oakley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Owner of the traveling Wild West Show that employed that sharpshooter, as well as Sitting Bull.",
          "answer": [
            "William Frederick Cody",
            "Buffalo Bill Cody"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Card game played by Wild Bill Hickok when he was shot dead, holding two pair.",
          "answer": [
            "five-card stud poker",
            "five card stud"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Quick mail service that used mounted riders and survived less than two years until the telegraph’s invention.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that granted 160 acres of land to citizens willing to work and improve the land for five years.",
          "answer": [
            "Homestead Act or Bill",
            "Law"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State where the Gunfight at the OK Corral took place in Tombstone.",
          "answer": "Arizona"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Coward” who shot and killed Jesse James in April 1882.",
          "answer": "Robert Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate leader whose guerrilla “Raiders,” including Jesse James, raided Lawrence, Kansas in August 1863.",
          "answer": [
            "William Quantrill",
            "Quantrill’s Raiders"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Divided Germany",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that occupied East Germany during World War II under Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "USSR",
            "CCCP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Barrier that divided Germany’s capital city starting in 1961.",
          "answer": "Berlin Wall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied method of supplying that city for 15 months in the late 1940s.",
          "answer": [
            "Berlin airlift",
            "descriptions of airdropping supplies, flying supplies in, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1945 conference in Germany where the allies divided their control of West Germany.",
          "answer": "Potsdam Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that served as West Germany’s capital and base of government, while its lawful capital was divided in the East.",
          "answer": "Bonn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that spiked in price in a namesake 1977 crisis, after which it was imported from Vietnam instead of Brazil.",
          "answer": "coffee crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "West German chancellor and advocate of Ostpolitik who resigned after his aide, Gunter Guillaume, was revealed to be an East German spy.",
          "answer": "Willy Brandt"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German leader who implemented the New Economic System and was succeeded by Erich Honecker in the early 1970s.",
          "answer": "Walter Ulbricht"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "British Canada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Neighbor country whose Articles of Confederation allowed for the annexation of British Canada.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "European rival country from whom Britain took Canada in the 1763 Treaty of Paris.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France"
        },
        {
          "question": "War ended by the aforementioned 1763 Treaty of Paris.",
          "answer": [
            "Seven Years’ War",
            "French and Indian War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Collection of former British colonies, including Canada and Australia, led ceremonially by Queen Elizabeth.",
          "answer": "Commonwealth of Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern city fought over in the Battle of the Plains of Abraham.",
          "answer": "Quebec City"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity whose trade was fought over by the Hudson’s Bay Company and coureurs de bois [coo-ror de bwa].",
          "answer": [
            "furs",
            "fur trade, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First Canadian Prime Minister, who took power after Britain granted semi-independence to Canada.",
          "answer": "John Alexander Macdonald"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who led the 1837 Upper Canada Rebellion, or the later Canadian Prime Minister named after this man who feuded with Lord Byng.",
          "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie and/or William Lyon Mackenzie King"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Near the end of a novel set in this country, two men reconcile when one gives the other a sympathy wreath for his dead wife and the other donates funds to build a new church. In a novel set in this country, the (20 pts)",
        "Smales family migrates to their servant’s village; that novel, July’s People, includes Nadine Gordimer’s prediction of a civil war and was once banned in Gauteng Province. The social activist (10 pts)",
        "Arthur Jarvis is murdered by Absalom Kumalo in this country in Alan Paton’s Cry the Beloved Country. For ten points, name this country, where those novels were written during the Apartheid era."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of South Africa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Between his stints on the Supreme Court, Charles Evans Hughes served in this Cabinet position under Harding and Coolidge. In this position, Elihu Root helped design the 1901 (20 pts)",
        "Platt Amendment, and another holder of this Cabinet position named John Hay formalized the Open Door Policy to keep trade with (10 pts)",
        "China balanced. Under Taft, a holder of this position promoted loans to countries in Latin America as part of “dollar diplomacy.” For ten points, name this Cabinet position that oversees foreign policy."
      ],
      "answer": "Secretary of State"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler was imprisoned in the fortress of Ku¨strin and nearly executed after he attempted to flee with his boyhood friend Hans Hermann von Katte, but he was captured and forced to watch Katte’s execution. This ruler constructed the (20 pts)",
        "Sansouci [sahn-soo- see] Palace and wrote the Anti-Machiavel, a work influenced by the ideals of Voltaire. This ruler invaded Silesia to begin the War of (10 pts)",
        "Austrian Succession, and fought Maria Theresa of Austria again during the Seven Years War. For ten points, name this King of Prussia known as “the Great.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II of Prussia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician’s 1956 trip to Ghana and tours for the US State Department inspired an album he made with Dave Brubeck, The Real Ambassadors. This man called President Eisenhower “gutless” for being slow to support the (20 pts)",
        "Little Rock Nine. According to legend, this man dropped his lyric sheet while recording “Heebie Jeebies,” leading to an early instance of scat singing. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Hot Five and Hot Seven sang about “trees of green” and “red roses too” in another song. For ten points, name this jazz trumpeter, nicknamed “Satchmo,” who sang “What a Wonderful World.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. During this event, a series of defenses called fleches [fleshes] were built by Pyotr Bagration, who commanded the left wing under Mikhail Kutuzov. This event, whose casualties were (20 pts)",
        "graphed by Charles Joseph Minard, resulted in its defenders setting fire to their own capital after their loss at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Borodino. A refusal to join the Continental System triggered, for ten points, what 1812 military campaign in which a French emperor conquered, but could not hold, Moscow?"
      ],
      "answer": "French invasion of Russia all three parts required,"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man engineered a worker’s cult around mangoes that lasted for one and a half years. This leader advised people to bang pots and pans in his (20 pts)",
        "Four Pests campaign; the resulting loss of sparrows caused a boom in the locust population. This leader baited anti-regime intellectuals with a brief period of liberalization known as the (10 pts)",
        "Hundred Flowers Campaign. Lin Biao and Zhou Enlai advised, for ten points, what the author of the Little Red Book and founder of the People’s Republic of China?"
      ],
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The terms of this legislation were debated by delegates from nine southern states in the Nashville Convention. By the terms of this legislation, Texas gave up claims to western lands in exchange for trading off ten million dollars of debt. In this legislation, (20 pts)",
        "California was admitted as a free state, but the New Mexico and Utah Territories were established under (10 pts)",
        "popular sovereignty. For ten points, name this deal brokered by Henry Clay and Stephen Douglas that many historians believe postponed the Civil War for a decade."
      ],
      "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A military dictator of this country was famed for making civil servants who were late to work do squat-jumps; that leader won an election as the head of the All Progressives’ Congress with support from this country’s (20 pts)",
        "Hausa ethnic group. This country was once led by Goodluck Jonathan, who lost the aforementioned election after being criticized for his weak response to a terrorist group led by (10 pts)",
        "Abubakar Shekau. For ten points, name this African country currently led by Muhammadu Buhari from the city of Abuja, the home country of Boko Haram."
      ],
      "answer": "Federal Republic of Nigeria"
    }
  ]
}